Okay בוקר
טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* officially ל"ד *lamed dalet*, we pick
up at the bottom of ל"ג ל"ד *lamed gimmel lamed dalet* and
we are dealing with the issue of איסור חל על איסור issur
chal al issur. *issur chal al issur* and the debate of רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* and בר קפרא Bar Kappara *Bar Kappara*
of, I'm sorry, of three scenarios: a non-כהן
kohen *kohen* who does the עבודה avoda *avodah* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, a כהן kohen *kohen*
who is בעל מום baal mum *ba'al mum* who does the עבודה
avoda *avodah* when it's טומאה tumah הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibbur*, and
and what was the third case? Oh, and non-כהן kohen *kohen* eating
a bird that you had מליקה melika *melikah* done to it. And
the question was was those two transgressions or one? And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* wants to see that this is part of a debate
of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur. *issur chal al
issur* and had a couple of explanations. One was the idea of
איסור כולל issur kolal. *issur kolel*, but that did not work for
the case of מליקה melika *melikah* and the bird because that was
only those came exactly at the same time. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that the debate is about איסור בבת אחת issur be-vas
achas *issur b'vas achas* and whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
who normally holds אין איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur.
*ein issur chal al issur* would agree that it would happen when
they both came at the same time. And that seems like a
pretty reasonable explanation except if you remember both רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
*Rabbi Chiya* and בר קפרא Bar Kappara *Bar Kappara* stood up, jumped
up and took oaths that רבי Rebbi, *Rebbe* said what they said,
that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* said that רבי Rebbi *Rebbe*
said two transgressions and בר קפרא Bar Kappara *Bar Kappara* said one.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying to figure out how there
could have been this misunderstanding. And it doesn't understand that for from
רבי חייא'ס *Rabbi Chiya's* perspective if even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* רבי *Rebbe* taught that you would be transgressed twice,
where could בר קפרא Bar Kappara *Bar Kappara* have ever heard from
רבי *Rebbe* that you only transgress once? And that's where we pick
up at the bottom of ל"ג ל"ד *lamed gimmel lamed dalet*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
three lines from the bottom: אלא ela לרבי חייא בר קפרא Bar
Kappara שיקרא קמשקר *Ella l'Rabbi Chiya Bar Kappara shikora kameshakeir*? According to
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya* is בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* lying?
If it's really true that בבת אחת b'vas achas, *b'vas achas* you're
חייב chayav *chayav* twice even according to the most lenient opinion, even
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*, how did בר קפרא
*Bar Kappara* ever hear the idea that you're only חייב chayav *chayav*
once? So אמר לך רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Amar lach Rabbi Chiya*,
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya* would say to you no, כי
אתנייה רבי לדידי תרתי לפטור אתנייה *ki asnaya Rebbe l'didi tarti l'ftor
asnaya*. When did רבי *Rebbe* teach to בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* when
he said you're exempt meaning you're only חייב chayav *chayav* once, it
was only two of the three cases. You'll remember we had three
cases, right? One was the זר zar *zar* בשבת *b'Shabbat*, okay, that
did work in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*.
The other was the בעל מום baal mum *ba'al mum* that worked
in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* בטומאה *b'tumah* even when it was
a case of טומאה tumah. הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibbur*, but the
question was whether it applies to him, okay, and שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*
of course is allowed for the עבודה avoda *avodah*. And the third
case was about the זר zar *zar* that ate the bird of
מליקה melika, *melikah* which is again permitted to the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*.
So these last ones are things that are normally permitted when you're
doing it the right way, but they are all doing it the
wrong way, okay. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said these cases could
be sequential. First you do the עבודה avoda *avodah* and then it
becomes שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, first you're בעל מום baal mum, *ba'al mum*
then you become טמא tamei, *tamei*. Okay, but this when the bird
becomes non-kosher to be eaten because you did the מליקה melika *melikah*
that's exactly the same time that it becomes a קרבן korban, *korban*
that can't be eaten by a non-כהן kohen *kohen*. So this is
a case, so these cases could be sequential, could be בבת אחת
b'vas achas. *b'vas achas*. This can only be בבת אחת b'vas achas.
*b'vas achas*. So if we're talking about the issue of בבת אחת
b'vas achas, *b'vas achas* how could he have ever heard one? So
what רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* is saying is no, no,
no, בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* heard רבי *Rebbe* talk about these two
cases. And he heard him say in these two cases you're חייב
chayav *chayav* only one because he was saying that these were sequential
and it was an issue of איסור כולל issur kolal *issur kolel*
and that would be and איסור כולל issur kolal *issur kolel* you
would not be חייב chayav *chayav* twice only one. And what he's
going to say is so בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* heard רבי *Rebbe*
teach these two cases in a case of sequential and איסור כולל
issur kolel, *issur kolel* and said one. בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* accidentally
inserted the third case in and therefore thought it wasn't about איסור
כולל issur kolel, *issur kolel* and sequential, thought it was about בבת
אחת b'vas achas. *b'vas achas* and that's why he got confused to
think that רבי *Rebbe* taught בבת אחת b'vas achas *b'vas achas* you're
also חייב chayav *chayav* only one.
Is sequential and איסור כולל issur kollel. *issur kolel* related?
No, well, sequentiality meaning איסור כולל issur kollel, *issur kolel* is always
when A happens and then B will be an added איסור issur
*issur*, it might add an איסור issur *issur* if it's an איסור
מוסיף issur mosif *issur mosif* or an איסור כולל issur kollel. *issur
kolel*. Okay, but it's not relevant to talk about איסור כולל issur
kollel.
*issur kolel*
when it's בבת אחת b'vas achas *b'vas achas*.
בבת אחת b'vas achas *b'vas achas* the whole point is it doesn't
matter. Okay, so he was teaching him a הלכה halacha. *halachah* about
איסור כולל issur kolel.
*issur kolel* when
it was sequential and בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* accidentally inserted this case
and this case could only be בבת אחת b'vas achas *b'vas achas*
and misunderstood that everything was about בבת אחת b'vas achas? *b'vas achas*.
What, and he's the one who swore he never heard? Well, he
got confused, it's like we all often misremember, okay. He didn't remember
that he didn't hear it that way. ואיסור כולל kolal. אתנייה *v'issur
kolel asnaya*, רבי *Rebbe* taught him the הלכה halacha *halachah* of איסור
issur כולל kollel? *issur kolel* when those two cases were sequential ואליבא
v'aliba, דרבי שמעון Shimon *v'aliba d'Rabbi Shimon*, and according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, maybe
even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose *Rabbi Yosei* who holds of איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur, *issur chal al issur* would hold
of it by איסור issur כולל kolel *issur kolel*, but he was
saying according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* you're only חייב
chayav *chayav* one in these two cases. And he meant when they
were sequential and it was an איסור issur כולל kolel *issur kolel*,
רבי *Rebbe*... if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. rejects איסור מוסיף issur mosif
he certainly rejects איסור issur. כולל. kolel, That's what Rabbi taught him.
וחזא בר בר קפרא לזר שאכל מליקה, V'chaza Ber Barkappara le'zar she'achal
melika, בר קפרא then saw the third case of זר שאכל מליקה,
zar she'achal melika, which could only be a case of בבת אחת,
be-vas achas. ואיידי דדמיא ליה v'aydi d'damya lei was very similar, right?
It was a non-כהן kohen and it was something that normally would
have been allowed if it was done the right way. So, ואיידי
דדמיא ליה ערבייהו, v'aydi d'damya lei arvibihu, he mixed it amongst, he
mixed it with the other two. In his mind, they all became
the same הלכה. halacha ועיון
בה, v'ayun bah, then he started looking at those three cases and
those three cases, the last one, which he accidentally mixed in to
no longer be talking about איסור issur כולל kolel, because it's all
בבת אחת. be-vas achas ולא אשכח אלא בבת אחת, v'lo ashcach ela
b'vas achas, the only common denominator of this new set that he
didn't realize that he had now changed was the idea of בבת
אחת. be-vas achas, וסבר מדא בבת אחת הא נמי בבת
אחת, v'savar mid'ha b'vas achas ha nami b'vas achas, if the case
of מליקה melika? can only be explained under בבת אחת, bevas achas?
the whole set is all about talking about בבת אחת. bevas achas
ומדהא לפטור הא נמי לפטור, v'mid'ha l'pattur ha nami l'pattur, and since
Rabbi taught me these are exempt, they're all exempt and therefore basically
he misremembered Rabbi. So Rabbi was teaching him הלכה halacha sequential, he
added this extra case, he misremembered, he thought the whole story was
about the fact of בבת אחת bevas achas. and that's how he
came to believe that Rabbi taught him בבת אחת bevas achas is
only חייב chayav once. All right, very nice. Moving up. What we
have seen is that there are three ways you could say איסור
חל על איסור. issur chal al issur, איסור מוסיף issur mosif is
easier than כולל. איסור מוסיף issur mosif expands the audience to whom
this object is forbidden. איסור מוסיף issur mosif, expands the types of
activities that are forbidden.
And this idea of בבת אחת bevas achas. which might be an
easier way in, because you don't have to say first A and
then B and can B happen after A when it all happens
at the same time? It's easier to say that even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would agree that that would work. Let's just get to
the משנה. mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you
on this idea that now we have said that they are arguing
about בבת אחת bevas achas אליבא דרבי שמעון. aliba d'Rabbi Shimon. Assuming
that's true, let's try to prove what the הלכה halacha is. So
we have a
ברייתא. braisa. And almost exactly this case. זר ששימש בשבת ובעל מום
ששימש בטומאה, Zar she'shimmesh b'Shabbos u'baal mum she'shimmesh b'tumah, exactly the two
of the three cases we were talking about. A non-כהן kohen. does
the עבודה avoda on שבת Shabbos or בעל מום does the עבודה
בטומאה avoda b'tumah even in the case of a קרבן ציבור. korban
tzibbur. יש כאן משום זר ומשום שבת, Yesh kan mishum zar u'mishum
Shabbos, so you transgress being a זר zar and שבת Shabbos, in
the first case, ומשום בעל מום ומשום טומאה u'mishum baal mum u'mishum
tumah and בעל מום and טומאה in the second case. דברי רבי
יוסי, Divrei Rabbi Yose, two transgressions. Like we saw, but now it's
no longer רבי חייא בר קפרא, Rabbi Chiya bar Kappara, now it's
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who we know
normally debate איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur So רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says two, ורבי שמעון אומר אין כאן אלא משום
זר ובעל מום בלבד. v'Rabbi Shimon omer ein kan ela mishum zar
u'baal mum bilvad. There is only the issue of the first issue
about being a זר zar and a בעל מום, not the second
issue that came later, שבת Shabbos, and טומאה. ואילו, v'ilu,
now, that's talking about two of the three cases and we see
it's a debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose, and רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon ואילו מליקה, v'ilu melika, the third case of מליקה melika. by
the bird and a non-כהן kohen? eating it, which could not be
sequential, which is only at the same time, שיירה, shiyarah, that was
left off of this ברייתא. braisa. Now, למאן שיירה, l'man shiyarah, for
who would you have left it off? Who would have had a
different פסק psak by the case of בבת אחת? b'vas achas? אילימא
רבי יוסי, Ilima Rabbi Yose, if it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose that
can't be. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is prepared to say you get
two transgressions even when it's sequential.
השתא רבי יוסי באיסור כולל מחייב שתים, Hashta Rabbi Yose b'issur kolal
mechayev shtayim, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would say that if it's sequential
and the second one is a little bit broader it can take
effect on top of the first one, he's okay with איסור חל
על איסור. issur chal al issur בבבת אחת מיבעיא, B'v'vas achas mibaya,
of course if they come at the same time then it's not
like one had precedent. So of course that would, you would transgress
two. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, would not have changed his position
in the case of מליקה, Melikah so he could have said the
third, he could have been talking about מליקה as well. So why
did the ברייתא braisa not talk about מליקה? It must be that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would have had a different position about מליקה.
I understand that, because it's because he wouldn't have needed to say
it.
So that's why. Okay, but fine,
yeah, all right, let's just go on.
אלא לאו רבי שמעון, Ela lav Rabbi Shimon, it
must be the reason it wasn't taught was because רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would not be able to say the same thing by it.
That רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. says one, but if it was a
case of them happening at the same time he wouldn't be able
to have the same פסק. psak. ובאיסור כולל הוא דפטר, u'b'issur kolal
hu d'pattar,
only when it's sequential and the second one is an איסור כולל
he says you're only חייב chayav. once, which is the two first
cases that were being discussed. אבל באיסור בבת אחת מחייב, aval b'issur
b'vas achas mechayev, but presumably the reason it had two of the
three scenarios,
why is it before we were talking about three scenarios and here
it's only talking about two? It must be that the third one
would have had a different הלכה halakha. and the only one it
would have had a different הלכה halakha, to would have been רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon So clearly you see that the same רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, who says only one. The reason he's not also saying
the case of מליקה is presumably in this case he would concede
that you are חייב chayav twice, cause that's a case of בבת
אחת. bevas achas. So we see, so the גמרא Gemara says אבל
בבת אחת מחייב, aval be-vas achas mechayev, תיובתא דבר קפרא תיובתא. tyufta
de-Bar Kappara tyufta.
That's a contradiction of Bar Kappara. If you believe what the גמרא
Gemara said yesterday, which of course you could question, but if you
accept the גמרא's Gemara conclusion yesterday that the debate of רבי חייא
and בר קפרא was a debate whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, would
agree of איסור בבת אחת issur be-vas achas. or not, this ברייתא
braita shows you that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not believe in
איסור בבת אחת. bevas achas, I don't know, I think it's a
pretty good proof. If we already have a context where three cases
were being talked about and this ברייתא braita discusses two, there was
a reason that the third one was left off. So I think
that it's a totally fine proof that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, holds
that זר מליקה zar Melikah is a different case. Okay now, if
you now דווקא davka bring the lens on it of the idea
of בבת אחת or whatever we could debate, but assuming what makes
this distinct is בבת אחת, I think that's a reasonable proof. But
I don't think the גמרא Gemara did a necessarily did a great
job proving what רבי חייא and בר קפרא were debating. Okay, so
I agree that I would not have said תיובתא דבר קפרא. tyufta
de-Bar Kappara. I would have said it's a proof that רבי שמעון
Shimon agrees בבת אחת חייב שתיים. be-vas achas chayav shtayim. Why שתיים?
shtayim?
Because, you know, the גמרא Gemara kept on saying before, "Oh, what
do we need this משנה Mishnah for?"
All right, but now that we have identified that there is a
something distinct about that third case, then we do need to talk
about it and we do need to identify whether it's different or
the same as the other cases. Okay, I think it is significant
that it's left off. I don't know whether to necessarily prove what
the גמרא Gemara says it proves. Okay, I certainly don't know whether
we can assume that the debate of רבי חייא and בר קפרא
is exactly the way the גמרא Gemara concluded. But anyway. All right,
so that's that. Now let's get to the משנה. Mishnah.
Now, במאי? bemai? Now the גמרא Gemara says one last question: זר
ששימש בשבת, zar she-shimmesh be-Shabbos, going back to the case of the
זר zar. that does the עבודה avoda on שבת, Shabbos, that we
say you're חייב chayav twice, or you could be חייב chayav twice,
because you did two עבירות aveiros at once. What were the two
עבירות? aveiros? A זר zar who did the עבודה and חילול שבת.
chillul Shabbos. So במאי, bemai, where did he do his חילול שבת?
chillul Shabbos? What act did he do? אי בשחיטה, Ee bi-shchita, if
he was שחיטה shechting the קרבן, korban. שחיטה בזר כשרה. shchita be-zar
keshera. A non-כהן kohen can do שחיטה shchita of a קרבן. korban.
So this is actually an interesting הלכה. halachah No, any קרבן. korban,
So actually an interesting הלכה, halachah which I bet you didn't know,
that the same if you're doing an עבודה on שבת Shabbos, in
the בית המקדש that's allowed, a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur you're bringing
the תמיד Tamid or you're bringing the מוסף, Musaf, you could have
a non-כהן kohen come and do the שחיטה, shchita, because that's part
of the עבודה and it's כשר kasher with a non-כהן. kohen Even
a woman! So there you go. Okay, so it can't be we're
talking about שחיטה, shchita, that wouldn't have been a problem. אי בקבלה
והולכה, Ee be-kabala ve-holacha, if it's catching the blood or bringing the
blood to the to the מזבח, mizbeach, טלטול בעלמא הוא. tiltul b'alma
hu.
That's just what, moving something? It's within four walls, what is it,
מוקצה? muktzah?
That's not what we're talking about. אי בהקטרה, Ee be-haktara,
so it's burning the limbs and the on the מזבח. mizbeach. וסבר
רבי יוסי הבערה ללאו ניתנה, V'savar Rabbi Yossi hava'ara le-lav nitna,
but remember, we're talking according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi right? The
debate was רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and רבי שמעון. Shimon Now רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, ironically, that if you make a fire on
שבת, Shabbos, you're not חייב מיתה. chayav misa. You're only transgress a
לאו, lav, because it's the one מלאכה melacha or maybe one of
the few מלאכות melachos that the תורה Torah explicitly labels you can't
do on שבת, Shabbos לא תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת. Lo
tivaru eish be-chol moshvoseichem be-yom ha-Shabbos. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, says,
"So why did it have to label it at all? It already
said don't do any מלאכה." melacha. It must be it labeled it
to tell me this wasn't as weighty as all the other מלאכות.
melachos. All other מלאכות melachos you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa, this is
just a לאו. lav. The one מלאכה melacha that's explicitly labeled. Exactly.
So according to this same רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose you wouldn't be
חייב מיתה chayav misa for burning something on a fire. And we're
presumably we're talking about how many קרבנות korbanos you have to bring,
you know, we're talking about things of equal weight weighty transgression. So
what did you do? אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha
bar Yaakov, you're not cooking, it's you're burning it. אמר רב אחא
בר יעקב בשחיטת פרו של כהן גדול. Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
bi-shchitas paro shel Kohen Gadol. Ah, here's the case. We're talking about
that it's יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's not שבת, Shabbos, it's יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. And the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has to bring
his ox, right, on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And the we know
that the עבודה of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is done only with
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So how about the שחיטה? shchita? Would
it go all the way back to the שחיטה shchita of something
that normally could even be done by a non-כהן? kohen
So that so we're going to assume that even that requires the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And therefore, it's a case where you did
a שחיטה, shchita, which you're not allowed to do on שבת, Shabbos
which everybody agrees is a מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos and this
is a case that שחיטה shchita wasn't כשר בזר kasher be-zar because
it was יום כיפור Yom Kippur and it had to be done
by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. All right, we were so...
And וכי שחיטה עבודה היא? ve-chi shchita avoda hi? Yeah, exactly.
בשחיטת פרו של כהן גדול, bi-shchitas paro shel Kohen Gadol, וכדברי אומר
שחיטת פרו של כהן גדול בזר פסולה, u-che-divrei omer shchitas paro shel
Kohen Gadol be-zar psula, according to the one that says that on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, a non-כהן cannot do the שחיטה shchita of
the פר par of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. The גמרא Gemara
says, "One minute. אי הכי, Ee hachi, if that's the
case, מהי אריא זר? mai irya zar? Why would it have to
be a non-כהן who did the שחיטה? shchita? אפילו כהן הדיוט נמי."
afilu kohen hedyot nami. Even a non-כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay? Because
according to that opinion, any non-כהן גדול kohen gadol is פסול pasul
to do the שחיטה shchita on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So the
גמרא Gemara says, "שזר אצלו קאמר." she-zar etzlo ka'amar. Fine, we didn't
literally mean a זר. zar. We mean somebody who was a זר
vis-à-vis this קרבן, korban, wasn't allowed to do this קרבן, korban. which
would mean somebody who wasn't the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. That's a
pretty big stretch. So the גמרא Gemara says a better answer.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מתקיף לה רב אשי, matkif
lah Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi says, "I don't understand." I don't understand
your problem. מידי חטאות קתני? Midi chataos katani? The ברייתא braita didn't
say we were debating how many sin offerings you have to bring,
so you should be bothered that doing a fire on שבת Shabbos.
is not a חייב מיתה chayav misa and not a sin offering.
We weren't talking about sin offerings. או לאוי קתני? O lavei katani?
Were we talking about how many לאוין lavin you transgressed?
אלא איסורי בעלמא קא חשיב. Ella issurei be'alma ka chashev.
We're just trying to figure out how many wrong things you did.
למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka mina? לכל רבנו שמעון גמרא? Lekol Rabbeinu
Shimon Gemara? And the only נפקא מינה nafka mina is not how
many lashes we give you and how many קרבנות korbanos you have
to bring, it's only are you more of a רשע rasha for
having done two עבירות aveiros or doing one עבירה, aveira, which is
what the גמרא Gemara said before, which is quite ironic to have
a major debate of תנאים, Tannaim, איסור כולל, איסור מוסיף, issur mosif,
or whatever, all to determine how much of a רשע rasha you
are, not how many חיובים chiyuvim you actually have, but anyway, we've
seen that before. Okay, so that was a fascinating discussion about איסור
חל על איסור, issur chal al issur. which was not in the
משנה mishna at all, it was a digression because the גמרא Gemara
quoted a ברייתא braita about a man sleeping with a woman who
is both his brother's wife and his wife's sister. Do you get,
does he transgress once or does he transgress twice? And the difference
between איסור מוסיף, issur mosif. when the object becomes forbidden to a
wider range of people, איסור כולל, when more things are forbidden, but
this object hasn't changed its status but more things in the same
class are forbidden, and,
which is harder to say איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al
issur? and איסור בת אחת, issur bas achas, which is presumably a
case that most would agree you would have both. Okay, so we
think we're done, but actually we're not done, and the גמרא's Gemara
going to continue this discussion in the context of the next משנה.
mishna. Yes?
What's the import of רב אשי? Rav Ashi? Is רב אשי Rav
Ashi a קשיא, kashya, no? Is it so reductionist, what's the import?
No, he's saying what, why does it bother you to figure out
what איסור this guy did on שבת, Shabbos and you didn't want
to say that he did the איסור of burning the limbs on
the מזבח mizbe'ach because that wasn't a חייב מיתה? chayav misa? We
weren't necessarily talking about חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay, now you're right,
once he gives that answer, it's less interesting in terms of the
implications of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur. in this
case. But okay, so when there's more interesting implications like two חטאות
chataos or two sets of lashes or who knows, then it'll have
those implications. But in this case, there wasn't that interesting implication. He's
not saying איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur, doesn't have
interesting implications, he's just saying it doesn't have to be what we're
talking about here. All right. Yes, very quickly.
Yeah, the dispute between רבי חייא and רב בר
קפרא, Rav Bar Kappara,
which רבי חייא is this?
I assume it's the generation after רבי, right? Because they're debating what
רבי taught.
So was he the, was this the same רבי חייא who was
the compiler of the תוספתא? Tosefta? Yes. That's shocking he not, that
they would say that he would misattribute something.
Well, in the end they made בר קפרא the one who made
the
mistake, at least on his suspect or whatever, whatever he did, he
did something that was not שחיטה shechita because that wasn't a problem
at all, or he did שחיטה shechita if he was פר של
כהן
גדול.
par
shel Kohen Gadol.
But no, it was שבת Shabbos here, then it was, then it
was עבירה.
aveira. Sorry, no, then it was the עבירה. aveira. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says משנה. mishna. שנים שקידשו שתי נשים. Shenayim shekiddeshu shtei
nashim. All right, so now we get to, now we maybe see
why the גמרא Gemara laid the groundwork for this because even though
it really wasn't relevant to the previous משנה, mishna, it's going to
be very relevant for this משנה. mishna. שנים שקידשו שתי נשים, Shenayim
shekiddeshu shtei nashim, two people married two women, completely
the men weren't related, the women weren't related. ובשעת כניסתן לחופה, Uvish'as
knisasan lachuppah,
and when it was time to go into the חופה, chuppah, which
is basically euphemism when they were going home that evening and going
to have sex, החליפו את של זה לזה ואת של זה לזה.
hechlifu es shel zeh lazeh ve'es shel zeh lazeh.
They accidentally mixed up the wives. Okay, so sort of like a
רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, except it's worse than a רחל Rachel
and לאה Leah because here each man is now sleeping with the
other man's wife. Okay, maybe it does mean in the חופה, chuppah,
maybe they had a דעק טיכל deck tichl and you couldn't see
who was behind the, who was underneath, you know, you
couldn't see the face.
Anyway, okay, but then they slept with them is obviously the point.
Okay, but remember, just because they mixed them up under the חופה,
chuppah, they were still married to the other woman, קידושין kiddushin preceded
the חופה. chuppah. Okay, so even if חופה chuppah isn't a euphemism,
even if it really means that their faces were totally veiled under
the חופה, chuppah, they're still married to the other woman and now
they're having sex with the other man's wife. Okay, הרי אלו חייבים
משום אשת איש. harei elu chayavim mishum eshes ish. So each one
transgresses adultery. ואם היו אחים, Ve'im hayu achim, if they happened to
have been brothers, משום אשת אח, mishum eshes ach, in addition to
adultery, they're transgressing brother's wife. ואם היו אחיות, Ve'im hayu achayos,
and if the wives were sisters, there was a רחל Rachel and
לאה Leah case, then they're also transgressing משום אשה אל אחותה, mishum
isha el achosah, a man and his, because it's his wife's sister,
he's already married to the other רחל Rachel and now he's sleeping
with לאה. Leah. ואם היו נדות, Ve'im hayu nidos,
and if they happened to be נדות nidos at that time, משום
נדה. mishum nidah. Then it's four transgressions. A cheeseburger! Right, well, but
that's not the same act, that's not the same act. Okay. ומפרישין
אותן שלשה חדשים. Umaphrishin osan sheloshah chadashim.
And after this happened and the error was realized, then you have
a enforced separation for three months before the women go back to
their rightful husbands. שמא מעוברות הן. Shema me'ubaros hen.
Because maybe they're pregnant and you want to make sure, you know,
if they're pregnant the child
would be... Well, we're assuming it was accidental and we're assuming everybody
did it accidentally and wasn't aware, and then it's not a case
of the woman being forbidden to her husband. Okay.
So חייבים chayavim would mean a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, but the
Gemara is going to deal with this, okay? But yes, if it
was intentional, how could they be going back to their husbands? And
then you have to make sure that they're not pregnant, ואם היו
קטנות ve-im hayu ktanot
however, if they were under age, שאין ראויות לילד she-ein re-uyot le-yeled
so they would not be able to have conceived or to give
birth more
literally, מחזירין אותן מיד machzirin otan mi-yad
then they can go back to their husbands immediately. ואם היו כהנות
ve-im hayu kehanot
and if they were
כהנות kehanot which is interesting, married to כהנים, Kohanim, daughters of כהנים,
Kohanim, נפסלו מן התרומה nifselu min ha-teruma they are invalid from תרומה,
teruma, presumably if married to כהנים, we will see about that in
the Gemara. Okay, let's take a look. החליפו hichlifu the Mishnah says,
literally means החליפו hichlifu means they exchanged their wives. So the Gemara
says מידי ברשיעי עסקינן midei berashia askinan are we dealing with wicked
people that are intentionally doing wife swapping? והתניא ve-hatanya we have a
Baraitha, דתני רבי חייא de-tani Rebbi Chiya Rebbi Chiya taught הרי כאן
שש עשרה חטאות harei kan sheish esrei chata-ot there will be sixteen
sin offerings. So there's the first answer, we are talking about it
was unintentionally. So for four sins: אשת איש eshet ish married woman,
אשת אח eshet ach brother's wife, אחות אשתו achot ishto wife's sister,
and נדה niddah and there are four people involved because although we've
consistently been talking about this all from the man's perspective, but
the woman is involved as well in this act and also transgresses
the same as the man. So even if everybody is a שוגג,
shogeg, so each person has to bring four sin offerings, that's sixteen
sin offerings. So אי במזיד ei be-meizid and if it's intentional מי
קא קרבן mi ka korban there wouldn't be a קרבן. korban. So
אמר רב יהודה amar Rav Yehuda Rav Yehuda said תני הוחלפו. tani
huchlefu. It okay, it shouldn't read they exchanged, it means the wives
were exchanged. It was accidental. הכי נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistabra
that also makes sense, דקתני סיפא de-katani seifa as it says at
the end, אם היו קטנות שאין ראויות לילד מחזירין אותן מיד im
hayu ktanot she-ein re-uyot le-yeled machzirin otan mi-yad that they can go
right back to their husbands if they were under age. So Gemara
says ואי במזיד ve-ei be-meizid if it was intentional מי שריא mi
sharya how is a woman allowed to go back to her husband
if it was intentional? So the Gemara says no that's not a
question by the case of minors, הא לא קשיא ha lo kashya
in the case of minors even if it was intentional that wouldn't
be an issue, פיתוי קטנה אונס נינהו pitui ktana ones ninnu
the seduction of a minor is considered to be forced or not
willed, which basically means statutory rape, okay, which means that consent of
a minor does not constitute consent. So therefore even if it was
intentional, the woman is only forbidden to her husband, it's quite interesting,
let's say the man was intentional but the woman was not in
an act of adultery, the woman is the fact that a woman
becomes forbidden to her husband is measured by the woman's intentionality, not
by the adulterer's, not by the man.
So in this case if the woman cannot be deemed as consensual,
she would not be forbidden to her husband even if it was
willful, even if it was intentional, that would not make her forbidden
to her husband if she's a minor.
She's being raped?
No, she's consensual but it's statutory rape, על פי דין al pi
din it's rape, her consent doesn't mean anything. על פי דין al
pi din rape. Yes, in practice it's consensual but halakhically it's deemed
as non-consensual.
So the Gemara says like this: אלא fine, so that's not a
proof. But here's the proof: דקתני מפרישין אותן שלושה חדשים de-katani mafrishin
otan shlosha chodashim
it says you make them wait three months, שמא מעוברות הן shema
me-ubarot hen lest they are pregnant, הלא מעוברות ha lo me-ubarot if
they're not pregnant, or one would say after three months, שריא sharya
they go back to their husbands. ואי במזיד ve-ei be-meizid if it's
intentional מי שריא mi sharya how could they be going back to
their husbands? אלא לאו שמע מינה הוחלפו ela lav shma mina huchlefu
it means it accidentally happened, שמע מינה. shma mina. So that's obviously
a very nice read and פשט pshat of the Mishnah, and that's
also consistent with the idea that we're not talking about how many
times you put them to death or how many times they're חייב
כרת chayav karet but how many קרבנות korbanot they would have to
bring.
Yes.
This idea that the woman is חייבת חטאת chayavat chatat also, so
it's not that there's an איסור for the woman to sleep with
two
brothers, it's that she's participating in this. Right. That is very well
said. Yes. So all of the עריות arayot are framed from the
perspective of the man. Right. But she is participating in it. Right.
So it doesn't say don't sleep with a man who's married to
your sister. No. The sin is a man is sleeping with his
wife's sister and she is participating in that sin of a man
sleeping with his wife's sister. Right. Which is pretty funny because she's
not חייבת chayavat for like לפני עיוור lifnei iver either, she's חייבת
chayavat for actually the sin itself. But yes, that is true. It's
not just the Gemara that is male-oriented, all of the איסורים issurim
of עריות arayot are defined from the man's perspective. But the Torah
does say in a few places that the woman is put to
death or whatever when he does an act of ערווה. ervah. Okay.
So now the Gemara says like this: top of ל"ד ע"א. lamed
daled amud aleph. ומאן
האי תנא דאית ליה איסור כולל ואיסור מוסיף ואיסור בת אחת. u-man
hai tanna de-it leh issur kolel ve-issur mosif ve-issur bat achat. So
now the Gemara says, well, one minute, how can you get four
times? Right? These are this is איסור חל על איסור. issur chal
al issur, Why is it איסור חל על איסור? So a woman
starts off as married to a guy. So then she becomes אשת
איש. eishes ish. Okay. Then you marry her sister. So then she
becomes אחות אשה. achos isha. Now that is a case of איסור
כולל. Remember this woman is not אסור assur to more people. She
was already אסור assur to every single man in the world. But
now that you're אסור assur to her sisters, you're then she also
right? Because you marry I mean you're married to your wife's other
sisters, you're also married to this sister of your wife even if
your wife doesn't have other sisters. So because your field has expanded,
not her, but your field, she gets included. That's איסור כולל, right?
People remember that basic difference from yesterday? Okay. So
that's that. Now after that she becomes oh wait I'm sorry. Oh
the moment your brother married her that was בת אחת, bas achas,
brother's wife and married woman. Then you married her sister that was
איסור כולל. Then she became a נדה. niddah. Now נדה niddah is
a איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. Why? She's אסור assur to more people
now. Who's she also אסור assur to? Her husband. Okay. So you
got איסור בת אחת issur bas achas when she was married she
was married woman and brother's wife. You married the sister it's איסור
כולל. Okay. She became a נדה niddah that's איסור מוסיף. issur mosif.
So if you're חייב chayav four obviously it assumes that in all
of those scenarios that we were talking about yesterday all of them
you say איסור חל על איסור.
Did she become נדה niddah first?
We're I'm not going to deal with other configurations. Let's just accept
that scenario. ומאן האי תנא דאיתא איסור כולל ואיסור מוסיף ואיסור בת
אחת? U-man hai tana d'isa issur kollel v'issur mosif v'issur bas achas?
Who's the תנא tanna that holds all three? Well just yesterday we
said or just yesterday because we're behind, we said that was also
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose potentially but we're going to go for another
one now to also says all three. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
רבי מאיר היא. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Rebbe Meir hi. It's
רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. Why? דתניא. D'tanya. יש אוכל. Yesh ochel.
Now we're going to get with simple לאוין lavin not necessarily with
כרת kares and מיתה missa and so on. יש אוכל אכילה אחת
וחייב עליה ארבע חטאות. Yesh ochel achila achas v'chayav aleha arba chatassos.
Oh I'm sorry I misspoke. We are dealing with חטאות. chatassos. Okay.
You can do one act of eating and have four sin offerings
ואשם אחד v'asham echad and one אשם asham which is also a
different type of a sin offering. Here it is: טמא, tamei you're
a טמא tamei person and you're going to be eating from the
שאכל חלב. she-achal cheilev. You ate the חלב cheilev of a קרבן.
korban, So if you're a normal person who eats חלב, cheilev, חייב
כרת, chayav kares, bring a חטאת. chatas. If you're a טמא tamei
person who eats from a קרבן, korban חייב כרת. chayav kares. חטאת.
chatas. So that's number two. והוא נותר. V'hu nosar. This חלב cheilev
is not only the חלב cheilev of a קרבן korban but it's
a day old and it's נותר. nosar. And if you eat נותר
nosar you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. Number three. והוא מן המוקדשים. V'hu
min hamukdashim. Okay, מוקדשים mukdashim we already talked about. ויום הכפורים. V'Yom
Hakippurim. And you did it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur which is
a חייב כרת. chayav kares. That's four. Okay so that's one act.
Oh no, I'm sorry. מן המוקדשים Min hamukdashim means that not only
are you חייב chayav for being a טמא tamei. eating a קרבן
korban, but you're also חייב chayiv, for מעילה me'ila and that's the
אשם. asham. So that's the fifth. That's the אשם. asham. רבי מאיר
אומר אם היתה שבת והוציאו בפיו חייב. Rebbe Meir omer im hay'sa
Shabbos v'hotzio b'piv chayav. If it was שבת Shabbos, and you were
chewing it as you were walking, you're חייב. chayiv, אמרו לו. Amru
lo. That's a that's six. אמרו לו אינו מן השם. Amru lo
einu min hasheim. That's a little irrelevant. Okay. Because there you might
be carrying it in your mouth but you're not חייב for the
act of eating. Now תוספות Tosafos actually says that's really a good
point. Like would רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir said if while I'm eating
it I have a I'm carrying a knapsack on my back? You
know if while you know you know what I mean? Who cares?
You know it's conceptually a different act. It's not relevant to this
discussion. It's not how many times could you be חייב for the
same act? It might physically be in your mouth but it's not
the act of eating. So תוספות Tosafos says no, maybe the point
is is that as you swallow it, okay, הלכתית halachically when you
carry you have to place something down. And there might be a
הלכה halacha? that the act of swallowing constitutes placing it down. So
maybe it actually is somehow in
the הלכה halacha basically.
Anyway we're not going to worry about that too much right now.
But that's what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says. So this is a
case of all three scenarios. What's the three scenarios of בת אחת,
bas achas, מוסיף, mosif, and כולל? So let's look quickly at רש"י
Rashi because I can't keep it all in my head. So רש"י
Rashi says like this, אם היתה. im haysa.
Okay. גמרא Gemara says like this.
You see the רש"י Rashi it says there's a line starts with
the word you see on the side where it says like פסחים
ע"ב Pesachim ayin-beis in like square brackets on the far right? Okay.
Go up one sentence above that. So he says like this. רבי
מאיר כולו דהכא משנצר בהמה זו, Rebbe Meir kulo d'hacha mishe'notzar beheima
zo, when the animal was born, והיא חולין, v'hi chullin, before it
was sanctified, נאסר חלבה באכילתה. ne'esar chelba b'achilasa. It starts with the
חלב cheilev being אסור. assur. ומותר בהנאה. U'mutar b'hana'ah. הקדישה, Hikdishah, it
was sanctified. מיגו דתוסף איסור הנאה על החלב. Migo d'tosaf issur hana'ah
al hacheilev. Now the
חלב cheilev is forbidden in a different way, in an additional way.
You can't even get benefit from it. So משום קדשים יתוסף נמי
איסור אכילה משום זרות. Mishum kodshim itsof nami issur achila mishum zarus.
So that's an איסור מוסיף. issur mosif Now I have to stop
for a moment to say that is a huge חידוש. chiddush. Basically
all of the evidence is against this, that we that איסור מוסיף
issur mosif is not when the איסור becomes more severe. איסור מוסיף
issur mosif, is when more people... forbidden to this object. Here we're
saying it was already אסור assur to everybody because of חלב. cheilev.
Now it's also אסור assur to everybody as well, but in a
more severe way; you also can't get הנאה. hana'ah. So Rashi calls
that איסור מוסיף, issur mosif. you should just be aware that's a
very questionable application of איסור מוסיף. issur mosif But we'll work with
Rashi for now. Okay, so that's how you got איסור מוסיף issur
mosif. when you sanctified it. ואף על גב דאיסורא קאי באכילה. ve'af
al gav de'issura ka'i ba'achila. Okay, באכילה. ba'achila.
Even though it was already אסור אכילה, assur achila, adding the איסור
הנאה issur hana'ah is מוסיף, mosif, which is questionable. הוי ליה נותר,
havei lei notar, then it became נותר. notar. So, now here's a
real מוסיף. mosif. מיגו דאתוסיף איסורא למזבח, migo de'itosif issura lemizbei'ach, although
it's already אסור assur to the whole world, it's now אסור assur
to someone else. Who's it אסור assur to other than the whole
world? The מזבח. mizbei'ach. You can't put it on the altar, God.
So משום מוסיף, mishum mosif, איתא נמי לכהן משום נותר. ita nami
lekohein mishum notar. So now we've got איסור מוסיף. mosif. הרי הנך
תרתי משום איסור מוסיף. harei hanach tarti mishum issur mosif. נטמא זה
nitma zeh שעד עכשיו היה מותר she'ad achshav haya muttar בחתיכת בשר
קדש. bechatichas basar kodesh. Now I became טמא. So I now am
forbidden not just on this חלב, cheilev, but on everything that's קודש.
kodesh. ועכשיו נאסר בהן. ve'achshav ne'esar bahen. So מיגו דמיתווספא בשאר חתיכות
migo demisvosefa bish'ar chatichos משום טומאה, mishum tum'ah, now since I can't
eat any קרבן, korban. anything קודש, kodesh, so the range of things
forbidden to me, not for the object, for me, is broader, that's
an איסור כולל. נאסר נמי בזו משום טומאה. ne'esar nami bazo mishum
tum'ah. והיינו איסור כולל. vehaynu issur kolel. So we got כולל and
מוסיף. mosif Now what's the, and then the what is the בבת
אחת? That's a little trickier. It's funny that you need to prove
anybody holds בבת אחת because that should be assumed that you hold
בבת אחת. I won't tell you what Rashi says, it's confusing. Tosfos
says the בבת אחת is
that it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur and שבת. Shabbos רבי מאיר אומר
אם היה שבת. Rabbi Meir omer im haya Shabbos. Who needed it
Shabbos? We already said one of the things you did was it
was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and you were eating it on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? Wasn't that one of the five? So if
it's שבת Shabbos. and you get both for שבת Shabbos, and יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, you're also not allowed to carry on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, right? So
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the שבת יום כיפור Shabbos Yom
Kippur and you get חייב both for carrying on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and carrying on שבת, that's the taste of בבת אחת. Okay,
so we have all three here. So you see רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir holds you can get all three. אמרו לו. amru lo. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. לרבי מאיר אליבא דמאן?
leRabbi Meir aliba deman? According to who of the רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua and רבי שמעון Shimon debate that we saw before is רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir going like? I'm sorry, not רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
and רבי שמעון, Shimon. I'm sorry, that was רבי יוסי and רבי
שמעון, that was contemporaries. According to another debate that we're going to
see of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, not
about איסור חל על איסור, but there's another thing to be factored
in here. So we got that you have four types of, it's
four types of ways in which the act of sex is forbidden,
it works because of כולל and מוסיף mosif, and בבת אחת and
it's according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but there's another factor here,
which this man was trying to sleep with his wife, and that
means that they were trying to do a מצוה. mitzvah. So the
sin occurred in the attempt to be doing a מצוה. mitzvah. We
have an idea, a debate, a long-standing debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that somebody who makes an error
in the process of doing a מצוה mitzvah is פטור patur from
a חטאת. chatas. So let's take a look. לרבי מאיר אליבא דמאן?
leRabbi
Meir aliba deman?
Who is he going like? אי אליבא דרבי יהושע? i aliba deRabbi
Yehoshua? If it's according to רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? האמר טועה בדבר
מצוה
פטור. ha'amar to'eh bidvar mitzvah patur. If somebody makes an error and
does even something like this, a חיוב כרת chiyuv kareis in the
attempt to perform a מצוה, mitzvah, you're exempt from a קרבן. korban.
אלא אליבא דרבי אליעזר, ela aliba deRabbi Eliezer,
it must be going according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who argues
on רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. אי בעית אימא, i ba'is eima, or
I could always tell you, לעולם אליבא דרבי יהושע, le'olam aliba deRabbi
Yehoshua, even according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. כי קאמר רבי יהושע,
ki ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua, when does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say you're
exempt? טועה בדבר מצוה פטור, to'eh bidvar mitzvah patur, that if you
make an error in doing a מצוה mitzvah you're exempt from a
קרבן. korban הני מילי גבי תינוקות. hani mili gabi tinokos. That's when
it's a case of infants. There's a מצוה mitzvah of מילה. milah.
You're the מוהל, mohel, and you had a ברית מילה bris milah
on שבת and a ברית מילה bris milah on Sunday, and you
accidentally went ahead and you gave the ברית מילה bris milah to
the Sunday baby on שבת. And the parents somehow didn't stop you
or whatever. Okay, so there you were מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, right?
Because you did a ברית מילה bris milah on a baby that
wasn't supposed to be נימול nimol today, but you were trying to
do a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so that's where he says you don't
have to bring the חטאת. chatas. So the גמרא Gemara says that's
that case. Why? Because דזמנו בהול, dezmano bahul, because there's a time
pressure, because you have to get today's ברית מילה bris milah done
today. So that time pressure gives you already a certain amount of
a forgiveness, of a latitude, but after the fact we can understand
what?
Mitigating factors, thank you, combined with the fact that you were trying
to do a מצוה, mitzvah, that gets you off the hook. But
here the man didn't have to say I first sleep with my
wife tonight. Okay, there was no time pressure. So you don't have
that mitigating factor and we could say, I'm sorry buddy, even though
you're trying to do a מצוה, mitzvah, you should have been a
little more careful.
Okay. So here והרי ve'harei we're saying that why here does the
guy bring חטאת? chatas? Wasn't he attempting to do a מצוה? mitzvah?
Doesn't רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say that attempting to do a מצוה
mitzvah and you do a, that you're exempt from a קרבן korban,
if you made a mistake in terms of how you were doing
the מצוה, mitzvah, not if you did some other. If you made
a mistake in how you're doing the מצוה. Mitzvah. And the גמרא
Gemara said yeah, he might say that by the case of ברית
מילה Bris Milah and infants because there was also the time pressure
and that also exempts you. In this case with the man sleeping
with the woman he thought was his wife, there was no time
pressure, so the fact that he was doing a מצוה Mitzvah is
not enough to exempt him. Yes, just still.
How does time pressure make a difference? Either way he had no...
like what is he going to say? I better check this is
my wife if I'm going to... you know what I mean? Either
way he has this whole intention to do a מצוה Mitzvah just
the same way.
Right. So clearly what the גמרא Gemara is saying here is that
it's not just the attempt, it's not just the attempt to do
the מצוה Mitzvah that is itself gets you off; it's somehow... it's
the same, you have בהול
והזיק קמא, bahul v'hizik kama, look, damage was...
look, you can go two ways. You could say basically what's getting
you off is the sense of sometimes people are under so many
different pressures that they're not considered to be even negligent. They're אונס,
ones, right? They were so pressured or whatever, so maybe you could
read it as doing the מצוה Mitzvah adds to the time pressure
just makes him considered אונס. ones. I don't think that's what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. I think the גמרא Gemara is still saying
the פשט, pshat, that it's doing the מצוה Mitzvah that gets you
off; but if there's a sense of a great degree of negligence,
then you can't sort of, you know, then anxiety, no? Yes, but
that's not what I'm saying. I'm saying that, I'm saying that we
have two factors here. בהול bahul makes you more of an אונס.
ones. Doing a מצוה Mitzvah is more saying like, okay, you were
negligent, you should bring a קרבן, but you get a pass because
you were doing a מצוה. Mitzvah. You were sort of in the
mode of trying to do the right thing. How do those two
factors work together is not clear. Is it that the doing of
the מצוה Mitzvah makes you more of the אונס? ones? Or is
it that no, you're basically exempt because you're doing a מצוה, Mitzvah,
but we can't give you that exemption if you have a high
degree of negligence, because then even if you were doing the
מצוה, Mitzvah, there's too much fault here to allow that. When the
fault level lowers a little bit, then we can give you a
pass because you were doing a מצוה. Mitzvah. So in this case
by the wife, that's why you're חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, because it
wasn't זמן ובהול. zman u'bahul. What? Yeah. What's the other way?
The key thing is the being בהול. bahul.
That's what I said, you could go the other way. You could
say the מצוה Mitzvah adds to the sense of אונס, ones, right?
Yeah, exactly. Right. When it comes to קריאת שמע, Krias Shema,
we say that you're exempt because—yeah, but that's also because you're טרוד
tarud and whatever. Anyway here you're doing a sin, you're not just
not doing a מצוה. Mitzvah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: So it could work even according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi
Yehoshua. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: One minute. אבל האי
כיון דאין זמן ובהול לא. Aval hai kivan d'ein zman u'bahul lo.
והרי תרומה, V'harei Terumah, I'll give you a similar case of תרומה
Terumah which is also debated by רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, דאין זמן ובהול, d'ein zman u'bahul,
that he's not under a time pressure, וקא פטור, v'ka patur, רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua exempts there as well, did not? היה אוכל בתרומה,
Haya ochel b'Terumah, a כהן was eating תרומה, Terumah, ואין זמן ובהול,
v'ein zman u'bahul, there's no pressure, you can eat תרומה Terumah anytime.
ונודע שהוא בן גרושה ובן חלוצה, V'noda she'hu ben grusha u'ben chalutza,
and then all of a sudden you got a report that actually
you were the son of a divorced woman, or חלוצה, chalutza, which
is similar. And therefore you are חלל, chalal, you're not a—you don't
have קדושת כהן kedushas kohen and you're not allowed to eat from
תרומה Terumah and you're like a זר. So what's the הלכה? halacha
רבי אליעזר מחייב קרן וחומש, Rabbi Eliezer mechayev keren v'chomesh, רבי יהושע
פטור. Rabbi Yehoshua patur. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you have to
pay the principal and 20% or really winds up being 25%, and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you're exempt. So there also you're doing
a מצוה, Mitzvah, you're eating תרומה, Terumah, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
is saying you're exempt. Of course the funny thing there is there
you're really an אונס, ones, right? Who needs the fact that you
were doing a מצוה? Mitzvah? You had no fault, you were totally
an אונס. ones. Anyway it's interesting, but the גמרא Gemara looks into
it through the same lens. So look, you're exempt even though it's
not זמן ובהול. zman u'bahul. אתמר עלה, Itmar ala, it was said
on it, אמר רב ביבי בר אביי, amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye,
הכא בתרומה בערב פסח עסקינן, hacha b'Terumah b'erev Pesach askinan, דזמן ובהול.
d'zman u'bahul. No,
we make that fit into our model. It was ערב פסח, erev
Pesach, you had to eat the תרומה Terumah because it was חמץ.
chametz. ואיבעית אימא, V'ibayis eima, and if you want I could say—so
that's one answer. It could go according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would not exempt you when there's no time
pressure. ואיבעית אימא, V'ibayis eima, if you want I could say going
back to באיסור בת אחותו, b'issur bas achoso, ואליבא,
I'm sorry, באיסור בת
אחת,
b'issur
bas
achas, excuse me, wasn't printed here well.
באיסור בת אחת, b'issur bas achas, excuse me. So that we're done.
One approach is that this is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and it's
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says you can have בת אחת, bas
achas, כולל, מוסיף, mosif. etc. How does it work in with the
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Maybe even רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua would agree because you're not time pressured. That's a separate
issue, that you're doing a מצוה. Mitzvah. By the way, it's worth
noting the גמרא's Gemara assumption that when the man is sleeping with
his wife, that's seen just the same מצוה Mitzvah as the כהן
eating תרומה Terumah and doing a ברית מילה Bris Milah of a
baby on שבת, right? Same degree of exemption that would have applied.
Now the גמרא Gemara says maybe we can actually—so that's that. But
now let's go back. We assumed the משנה Mishna only worked if
because of בת אחת, bas achas, כולל, and מוסיף. The גמרא's Gemara
saying you know what? I could give you all those cases in
the משנה, Mishna, remember בת אחת bas achas is the easiest because
it's not one thing was first and the other thing can't come
on because the other thing's already there. Everything is happening at the
same time. The גמרא's Gemara saying I could explain the משנה Mishna
that all four cases happened at the exact same moment. Let's see
how that works. The גמרא Gemara says like this: ואיבעית אימא V'ibayis
eima forget— Forget רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. This is בת אחת Bat
Achas and
it could even be רבי שמעון who normally says you don't say
איסור חל על איסור, but this משנה Mishnah is all four things
happened in the same moment. Now how could all four things happen
in the same moment? So we already know about wives and brothers
and I'm sorry married woman and brother's wife. Now how could it
also be your wife's sister at the same moment that this how
could my brother married לאה Leah and she become my wife's sister
at the same she become his wife at the same moment she's
my wife's sister. If I married רחל Rachel first then she started
being my wife's sister. If I married רחל Rachel after then she
was my wife's sister after.
All right so Michael you remember that I mean so if we
did how did we exactly synchronize? How could you exactly synchronize the
moment I marry רחל Rachel and the moment he marries לאה? Leah?
So the way you can synchronize it is you do it through
a שליח shaliach and the שליח shaliach is representing multiple parties. So
let's take a look. Okay then we're going to have to deal
with the נדה niddah case. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
בשלמא כולהו משכחת להו Bishlama kulhu mishkachas lehu I can get the
three out of the four. דשוינהו שליח Deshavinu shliach
the brothers made one guy a שליח. shaliach. So the two brothers
ראובן Reuven and שמעון made Michael here their שליח, shaliach, ראובן Reuven
to marry רחל Rachel and שמעון to marry לאה. Leah. Okay so
that might have been two acts. Except very conveniently רחל Rachel and
לאה Leah made somebody דבורה Devorah could be a man but okay
דבורה Devorah a שליח shaliach to accept their קידושין. kiddushin. So Michael
and דבורה Devorah get together. Michael gives them two פרוטות, perutot, gives
two פרוטות perutot to דבורה Devorah in one act. She accepts those,
one for רחל Rachel one for לאה Leah and in that exact
second שמעון is married to ראובן Reuven is married to רחל Rachel
and שמעון is married to לאה Leah and they become married woman
and wife sister at the exact same second. דשוינהו שליח ושוינהו אינהו
שליח Deshavinu shliach v'shavu inhu shliach and the wives
and the women made a שליח. shaliach. ופגע שליח בשליח Upaga shliach
b'shliach and the two שליחים shaliachs got together and did it all
at the exact same second. So we can have all three statuses
of married woman, wife sister, and brother's wife at the same second.
But how about נדה? niddah? How does נדה niddah happen at the
same second? Either she was a נדה niddah before or she became
a נדה niddah after. All right you're too smart Michael but if
she just so how do we have a stopwatch we knew that
at that second they became a נדה? niddah? All right so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא נדה היכי משכחת לה Ella
niddah heichi mishkachas lah how do you get
the נדה niddah case?
So אמר רברם אמר רב Amar Rabram Amar Rav
now I'm going to read this like תוספות's Tosafot גרסא girsa I'm
not going to bother you with what רש"י's Rashi גרסא girsa is.
בשופעת מתוך Beshofes mitoch not י"ג yud gimmel but ג' שנים gimmel
shanim ג' לאחר שלשה gimmel l'achar shlosha that
the woman was bleeding, was a נדה niddah from before she was
three years old and then now literally it says here continuing to
bleed from so she started having her cycle before her third birthday
and it continued after her third birthday. But it really just means
she was still a נדה niddah during her third birthday which means
what? This girl רחל Rachel and לאה Leah happened to actually be
both underage. So actually it wasn't they who made a שליח shaliach
it was their father who made a שליח shaliach to accept the
קידושין kiddushin therefore Michael representing ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Now they're underage
so if they're underage there's no yet any איסור because it's not
an act of ביאה biah with them the גמרא Gemara's considers. Sex
with a girl under three is I mean again this is so
horrific to think about but the גמרא Gemara considers that that doesn't
even constitute an act of ביאה. biah. So therefore therefore at the
moment in a way it even solves the other problems because you
don't have to have the exact moment of קידושין kiddushin at the
same. As long as they're under three there's no איסור. Then when
they become three and if they're already נדות niddas at the moment
that they become three years old, right? Then all of the איסורים
issurim apply. So if they've already been married off by their father
right from before they were three but yet the איסורים issurim aren't
yet relevant because they're not yet considered an act of ביאה. biah.
Then they become and they're also נדה niddah at the second that
they become three then all the איסורים issurim apply. אשת אח, Eshes
ach, אחות אשה, achos isha, and נדה. niddah. Okay so that's the
answer. Okay so לאחר שלשה achar shlosha לחיובנהו L'chiyuvinuhu so the גמרא
Gemara says that's the לחיובנהו chiyuvinuhu that in order to make them
חייב when they become three. Now what about the brothers though? Because
the brothers are
why does this have to work in both directions?
Because they bring חטאות chataos too, right?
All right right because oh no no
no so that works for why the brothers would bring חטאות. chataos.
But then the women if they have to be bringing the חטאות,
chataos, they only become אסור assur when they become twelve, right? That's
when they become חייב for their acts, right? But at that moment
right their prohibition to I'm getting a little confused. So the
brothers already existed. Why would that not be בבת אחת?
Well if the brothers were already adults
this would work if
the...
They became three and they were נידה. niddah. It's all about the
נידה niddah case. They became three and they were נידה, niddah, then
the two brothers became—all the—all the status for the brothers towards them
happened at that exact moment. Okay, wonderful. So that's how the brothers,
it's בבת אחת. But now let's say they go to the מקוה
mikvah after they're three and before they become בת מצוה. bat mitzvah.
Then at the moment they become בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, right, so
they're not yet—they're not a נידה, niddah, okay, and it's not—or if
they went to the מקוה mikvah and then they became a נידה
niddah again. The prohibition of נידה niddah from their perspective when they're
אסור, assur, when they're adults, wasn't בבת אחת, right? It happened sequentially.
So therefore the case would be they didn't go to the מקוה
mikvah from the time they had their period at the age of
three until they became בת מצוה. bat mitzvah. So even when they
now become בר חיובא, bar hiyuva, obligated, and it would be a
sin for them, the prohibition of נידה niddah is the same prohibition
that was in effect from the time that it was that status
vis-a-vis the brothers. Okay?
Nine years to figure out—that was the wrong
word—Exactly,
so—well, no, no, no, maybe for the first nine years, whatever, okay,
maybe they got mixed up only when they started when they had
sex after their בת מצוה. bat mitzvah. They didn't have sex when
they were three, that's just when the איסור took effect. Okay, so
וחיובא דידהו מתוך שתים עשרה ולאחר שתים עשרה לחיובא דאינהי. vechiyuva deidhu
mitoch shtem esrei ule’acher shtem esrei lechiyuva de’inei. So to make the
men חייב, it’s when they become three years old, and to make
the women חייב, it’s that they had the same status when—and that’s
the case of the משנה. Mishnah. That’s if you want it to
work according to רבי שמעון, we could always have it work according
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Let’s try to get a little further,
let's actually turn the page today. מפרישין אותן, mafrishin osan, so you
separate them so you make sure they're not pregnant and it's not
a case of ממזרות. mamzerus. והא אין אשה מתעברת בביאה ראשונה. veha
ein isha misaberes bive’ah rishonah. The גמרא Gemara has an amazing—a fascinating
assumption that was believed in the ancient world, that a woman could
not become
pregnant—many people still believe it today—a woman could not become pregnant on
the first act of sex. So how was it if they only
slept with the—did—they did this wrong once, why do you have to
be afraid they're pregnant? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה שבאו
ושנו, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha sheba’u veshinu, they didn't
just do it once, they had sex a second time. ואלא הא
דתני רבי חייא הרי כאן ט"ז חטאות, ve’ela ha detani Rabbi Chiyya
harei kan tes-zayin chatos, רבי חייא says sixteen sin offerings. So if
they had sex twice, תלתין ותרתין הוו, taltin usartin havu, thirty-two sin
offerings. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולטעמיך, ultameich, one minute, according to
you, רבי אליעזר דמחייב על כל כח וכח, Rabbi Eliezer d’mechayev al
kol koach vekoach, we’re going to find out later that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says that every type of, literally,
like strength, but really means like, you know, every, you know, even
in the act of sex, even if the couple never fully separated,
but like every type of thrusting essentially is another act of sex.
So that's—טובא הוו, tuva havu, it also wouldn't be sixteen, how many,
you know, how long—how long the sex act was going on according
to him, it could have been a hundred חטאות. chatos. That's his
position. אלא בביאה ראשונה קא חשיב, ela bive’ah rishonah ka chashiv, we're
not doing the math like that. We're saying the first act, okay,
we're not going to figure out how many times—how long that act
went, we're not going to figure out how many other acts there
were. From the moment of the first act, there were sixteen sin
offerings. הכא נמי בביאה ראשונה קא חשיב, hacha nami bive’ah rishonah ka
chashiv, so here too we're talking about the first act of sex
and that's it. אין הכי נמי, in hachi nami, there might be
more depending on how long it went and how many other acts
there were. Okay, but the concern that she's pregnant, that would be
a case if they had sex a second time. This is the
גמרא's Gemara assumption, we're not concerned she's pregnant if they only had—if
it was the initial act when she was a virgin, she had
been a virgin before. So now אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar
lei Rava leRav Nachman, רבא Rava says to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
והא תמר דבביאה ראשונה איעברה, veha Tamar devive’ah rishonah i’abra, but how
about
תמר, Tamar, who became pregnant with Judah on the first act of
sex? Now, of course that's bizarre, since when was תמר Tamar a
virgin? So we're going to see in a minute that the גמרא
Gemara is going to assume that תמר's Tamar's act of sex with
Er and Onan was not vaginal sex. Okay, and therefore, since she—and
we have a tradition—I mean it doesn't say anywhere in the text,
but we have a tradition that the first time she actually had
vaginal sex was with Judah, and we know she became pregnant because
he only had sex once with her, ולא יסף עוד לדעתה. velo
yasaf od lada’ata. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה תמר באצבע
מיעכה. amar lei Tamar be’etzba mi’acha. No, תמר Tamar had first removed
her hymen with her finger. דאמר רב יצחק כל מועכות של בית
רבי, de’amar Rav Yitzchak kol mu’achos shel beis Rebbi, all—apparently in רבי
יהודה הנשיא's Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi's household this is what the girls would
do, they would actually remove their hymens before they would have had
sex, and all of them תמר שמן, Tamar sheman, they would give
them the name תמר, Tamar, okay, don’t—maybe as a nickname, because that's
what's assumed to be what תמר Tamar did. It’s funny, these like
legends or assumptions of what—of what actually had happened. It's actually quite
interesting, because there actually is evidence that, you know, there's a הלכה
halakha that a bride becomes—considered a נידה niddah on the wedding night
because of this whole הלכה about, what do you call it, about
דם בתולים, dam besulim, that we consider the hymenal blood, we treat
it rabbinically, it's actually post-Talmudic, we treat it at, or whatever, starts
towards the end of the time—the גמרא—anyway, Gemara we treat it as
if it were נידה niddah blood. So there's actually, you know, evidence
of practices of women, and people talk about it now
as... The presumably you don't believe was the hymen getting in the
way, she removed the hymen and that's how she could become pregnant.
Okay. ולמה נקרא שמה תמר? V'lama nikra sh'ma Tamar? Why would they
call her name Tamar? שמעכה באצבעה She'ma'acha b'etzba'ah because that's what Tamar
did. Okay. והא הוה V'ha hava now the גמרא Gemara says: How
could you say Tamar was a virgin? והא הוו ער ואונן, V'ha
havu Er v'Onan, didn't she have sex with Er and Onan? That's
pretty explicit in the story. ער ואונן שמשו שלא כדרכן. Er v'Onan
shimshu shelo k'darkan. No, that was not vaginal sex, that was anal
sex, and that's why it was not—it did not rupture the hymen.
And the issue here was if the hymen was still there, it
would prevent her from becoming pregnant.
Yes. What? The whole Er
and Onan's fault was that they withdrew before, but with anal sex
you can't...
Well, that's how the גמרא Gemara presumably is reading it, that the
idea of the reason it says וישחת ארצה v'shichet artza was he
had sex in not—it doesn't mean that he withdrew early, which is
how we tend to read it, but the גמרא Gemara reads that
וישחת ארצה v'shichet artza was he was doing—having sex in the way
in which necessarily it would have been וישחת ארצה. v'shichet artza. Okay,
but yes, simple sense of the verse is that he chose to
withdraw early, right? So the גמרא Gemara says... so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. והא הוה, V'ha hava, שמשו שלא
כדרכן. shimshu shelo k'darkan. מיתיבי, Meseivei, I'll ask you on this. We
say: כל עשרים וארבע חודש דש מבפנים וזורה מבחוץ דברי רבי אליעזר.
Kol esrim v'arba chodesh dash m'bifnim v'zoreh m'bachutz divrei Rabi Eliezer. If
you have a woman that's nursing, and we learned before that you
don't want her to get pregnant because that will seem to interrupt
the nursing, so the גמרא Gemara before used the issue about a
מוך, moch, some type of a—of a sponge. But רבי אליעזר Rabi
Eliezer says: No, you know what you do? You do or you
practice early withdrawal. Okay, literally you thresh on the inside and you
winnow on the outside. Okay, so you can figure out the metaphor
there,
okay. Do people know the agricultural act, right? דש Dash is when
you trample on the seed and you loosen the chaff from the
wheat, and then the winnowing is when you throw it up and
the wind blows away the chaff, okay. So you're sort of one
is sort of getting everything ready to be separated and then it's
sort of obviously talking about, you know,
about then separating it. Well, yeah, but the other word I was
looking for was... what's the word? Anyway, it doesn't matter. Having, anyway,
but it's about having the seminal emission. So anyway, so for twenty-four
months, that's what you do, you practice early withdrawal, and that's how
you solve the problem of not becoming pregnant, דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei
Rabi Eliezer. That's what Eliezer says. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so the
rabbis said back to him: הללו אינו אלא כמעשה ער ואונן. Halalu
eino ela k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan. No, that's not acceptable. That's acting like
Er and Onan did. Okay, that's Onanism. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says: So you see that Er and Onan did early withdrawal. It
wasn't ביאה שלא כדרכה. biah shelo k'darkah. So the גמרא Gemara says:
כמעשה ער ואונן ולא
כמעשה ער
ואונן. K'ma'aseh Er v'Onan v'lo k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan. It was like what
they did, similar but not identical. Thank you. כמעשה ער ואונן דכתיב
והיה אם בא אל אשת אחיו ושחת ארצה, K'ma'aseh Er v'Onan d'chtiv
v'hayah im ba el eshet achiv v'shichet artza, that it was true
that the semen was expelled outside of the body. ולא כמעשה ער
ואונן, V'lo k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan, but not exactly the same. דאילו התם
שלא כדרכה, D'ilu hatam shelo k'darkah, there it was—it was ביאה שלא
כדרכה biah shelo k'darkah was it was not vaginal sex. והכא כדרכה,
V'hacha k'darkah, and here it was. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says: בשלמא אונן דכתיב ושחת ארצה אלא ער
מנלן? Bishlama Onan d'chtiv v'shichet artza ela Er minalan? How do we
know that was Er's sin as well? So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק דכתיב וימת גם
אותו. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak d'chtiv v'yamet gam oso. He also
was killed by God. אף הוא באותה מיתה מת. Af hu b'osah
misah meis. In the גם gam that means even he was doing
the same. Now the גמרא says: בשלמא אונן משום לא לו יהיה
הזרע. Bishlama Onan mishum lo lo yihyeh hazara. We know that Onan
did it so that because he knew it wouldn't be his—child wouldn't
be named after him. This is very relevant to all the whole
story of יבום. yibbum. He felt somehow in some metaphysical way it
wouldn't be his child. אלא ער מאי טעמא עבד הכי? Ela Er
mai ta'ama avad hachi? Why did Er? So the גמרא says: כדי
שלא תתעבר ויכחיש
יפיה. K'dei shelo sisaber v'yachish yofyah. She was beautiful, he didn't want
her to get pregnant, okay, and she would make her—would make her
look less beautiful. But since it says that Onan did like Er
did, so that it says that whatever Onan's sin was that shows
us what Er's sin was as well. Now I just have to
say one sentence about—so actually we did a pretty good job getting
close to catching up, but I do have to say, this גמרא
is extremely significant in terms of the הלכה question as it relates
to marital sex and about the question about
ejaculating—the man ejaculating outside of his wife. Is that forbidden? The גמרא
seems to—seems to condone it. It's מעשה ער ואונן ma'aseh Er v'Onan
and so on. But on the other—there's another גמרא that seems to
say that there's no problem with husband and wife having ביאה שלא
כדרכה, biah shelo k'darkah, even though clearly that leads to the semen
being expelled outside of the wife. So there's an interesting debate in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. Some say ביאה שלא כדרכה biah shelo k'darkah is
only allowed if it does—if it's without seminal emission, and that even
in the context of marital sex the semen—it only—not—it's only not זרע
לבטלה zera l'vatalah if semen is—you
know—is—if seminal emission happens, you know, during the act of vaginal sex.
But the other approach, תוספות, Tosafot, says is: No, actually, any—anything in
the context of marital sex would not be considered זרע לבטלה zera
l'vatalah and whether
it's... Condemned. I said condoned before what I meant condemned. I’m sorry,
go back and reverse that word. Anyway, why is it being condemned
here in the case of in the case of early withdrawal? So
I just want to read you two very important ר"י *Ri* in
תוספות *Tosafot*. You see the תוספות ולא כמעשה ער ואונן *Tosafot v'lo
k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan* towards about ten lines from the bottom where it
says ואומר ר"י *v'omer Ri*, right next to the word בגז ושאר
דברים *b'geza v'sh'ar devarim*? People see that? The word בגז *b'geza*. The
תוספות ולא כמעשה ער ואונן *Tosafot v'lo k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan*. Go about
ten lines over on higher than the word התורה
*haTorah*. You see where it says התורה *haTorah*? Go the תוספות *Tosafot*
beginning with that, go ten lines up where it says ואומר ר"י
*v'omer Ri*. Okay. ואומר ר"י דהתם גמרא *v'omer Ri d'hatam Gemara* over
in נדרים *Nedarim* that sounded like anal sex was allowed. First answer
is the following: מיירי בלא הוצאת זרע דשרי *mairi b'lo hotza'at zera
d'shari*. That's when it didn't lead to seminal emission. דכיון דליכא השחתת
זרע לא הוי כמעשה ער ואונן *d'keivan d'leika hashchatat zera lo havei
k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan*. So that's one answer. ועוד אומר ר"י *v'od omer
Ri*. The ר"י *Ri* also says דלא חשיב כמעשה ער ואונן אלא
כשמתכוון להשחית הזרע *d'lo chashiv k'ma'aseh Er v'Onan ela k'shemitkaven l'hashchit ha-zera*,
ורגיל לעשות כן תמיד *v'ragil la'asot ken
tamid*. Okay. So it's all about destroying the
semen not as a way of preventing pregnancy, as a way of
avoiding natural sex, not whatever, vaginal sex. Okay. אבל באקראי בעלמא ומתאווה
לבוא על אשתו *aval b'akrai b'alma u'mit'aveh lavo al ishto*, if it's
just done because this is the way the couple wants to be
having sex and having their sexual activity and it's not done as
a way of early withdrawal to prevent pregnancy, שלא כדרכה שרי *shelo
k'darkah shari*, then it's allowed, דאמר בנדרים כל מה שאדם רוצה לעשות
באשתו יעשה *d'amar b'nedarim kol mah she'adam rotzeh la'asot b'ishto ya'aseh* etc.
And this is important because the רמ"א *Rama* actually rules according to
this second idea of the ר"י *Ri*, which is very important in
terms of people's understanding of what the תורה *Torah* does or does
not allow, הלכה *halacha* does or does not allow. In the context
of marital sex, according to the way the רמ"א *Rama* rules following
the ר"י *Ri*, הלכה *halacha* actually allows, it doesn't matter where the
seminal emission takes place, where the ejaculation takes place, anything in the
context of marital sex is not זרע לבטלה *zera l'vatala*. Okay. So
that was certainly an interesting.